let's see two trigonometric facts proved
visually in 2
minutes let's draw a right triangle
where one of the angles is labeled by
the Greek letter Theta assume the
hypotenuse has a length of one and the
opposite side then has a length of s of
theta the complimentary angle is Pi / 2
minus Theta we can take a second copy of
this triangle and reflect it creating a
larger isos triangle as shown here this
triangle has an angle 2 Theta and the
opposite side length is then 2 * the S
of theta we can use this triangle in two
different ways first of all from the law
of ss we see that s of 2 thet / 2 sin of
thet must equal the S ofun / 2 - thet /
1 this means that sin of 2 thet = 2 sin
of thet * the sin ofk 2us thet but the S
ofk 2 - thet is equal to the cosine of
thet therefore we see that sin of 2 thet
= 2 * * the S of thet * the cosine of
theta now let's apply the law of cosin
to the triangle pictured from the law of
cosin we see that 2 * the S of th^ 2 = 1
2 + 1^ 2 - 2 * 1 * 1 * the cosine of 2
thet dividing this equality by two and
isolating the cosine of 2 Theta we see
that cosine of 2 thet = 1 - 2 * sin^2 th
we have used one triangle diagram along
with with the law of ss and the law of
cosin to prove that sin of 2 thet = 2 *
the sin of thet * cosine thet and cosine
of 2 thet = 1 - 2 * the sin^2 of thet
these are known as the double angle
identities for S and cosine implicit in
this diagram is that the angle Theta is
acute do you think the identities hold
when Theta is obtuse can you prove it is
there a visual proof showing the double
angle identities in that
case